<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Petersen</title>
    <link>http://ex-nerd.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Petersen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 20:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ex-nerd.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Resumé:  Chris Petersen</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 00:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/resume/</guid>
      <description>Hi, you&amp;rsquo;ve found my &amp;ldquo;full&amp;rdquo; resume (i.e. curriculum vitae). It isn&amp;rsquo;t tailored for any specific job application, and contains a very wide sampling of skills and experience (often not specifically related to my chosen profession in technology). I mostly use it as a conversation starter before providing a more concise/professional PDF version.
This is always my most up-to-date resume — if you ask me for an updated version, I will just send you this URL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinds of Diabetes: Car Analogy</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/kinds_of_diabetes_car_analogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/kinds_of_diabetes_car_analogy/</guid>
      <description>Diabetes Mellitus is a 500 year old term that describes the sweet-smelling urine of people whose bodies have stopped being able to regulate blood sugar properly.
We now know that it refers to a family of different (and largely unrelated) diseases that all have the same symptoms before doctors can determine what has caused them. People &amp;ndash; even doctors &amp;ndash; still have trouble understanding the differences between these diseases, so I tried to come up with a simple and (hopefully) humerous analogy by thinking of each disease as a problem with your car.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type 1 Diabetes Name History</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/t1_name_history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/t1_name_history/</guid>
      <description>This page is sort of a living document about my research into the naming history of autoimmune diabetes mellitus, more commonly known as Type 1 Diabetes.
There are obviously a lot of missing sections but I&amp;rsquo;ve been promising to get this posted for several years and I figure this is the best way to encourage myself to finish.
Diabetes Mellitus The name &amp;ldquo;Diabetes Mellitus&amp;rdquo; dates back roughly 500 years, and awarness of the disease by other names (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making a Trossingen Lyre</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/making/trossingen-lyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/making/trossingen-lyre/</guid>
      <description>The Trossingen Lyre was uncovered in a 6th century gravesite in modern day Germany, and represents the most complete Anglo-Saxon lyre found to date. After making a prototype lyre out of plywood (links and more info for that coming soon), I decided to try my hand at this more difficult project.
This is an ongoing project, so I will be updating this page as often as I can.
You can read more about the original lyre in the German Wikipedia article about the Trossingen Lyre (English translation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participate in Clinical Research!</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/clinical_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/clinical_research/</guid>
      <description>Photos like this one are fairly common in Type 1 Diabetes forums, usually accompanied by a comment like &amp;ldquo;DKA sucks!&amp;quot;, making light of the extremely unpleasant and occasionally deadly Diabetic Ketoacidosis. I decided to post a similar photo but with a positive story behind it. So this is me, sitting in a hospital bed in the research wing of a local hospital while they spent several hours measuring how my body reacts when I drink a high carb/protein shake and don&amp;rsquo;t take insulin for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type 1 Diabetes Resources</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/resources/</guid>
      <description>I plan to eventually write about a bunch of these topics individually. Until then, here is my collection of links to a number of diabetes-releated topics that I have found especially helpful.
Blogs to read  Melitta is my favorite advocate about adult-onset T1, and always has great information with a strong emphasis on science and research.  http://adultt1diabetes.blogspot.com/   Gary Scheiner is the author of the amazing Think Like a Pancreas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Low Carb Waffles</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/low-carb-waffles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/low-carb-waffles/</guid>
      <description>Living with Type 1 Diabetes means that I have to closely watch my carbohydrate intake, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier to do this by eating low-carb foods that make the math easier. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up on some of the finer things in life &amp;ndash; like waffles &amp;ndash; I spent some time formulating a decent substitute for carb-heavy grain-based waffles. This lets me have a fairly large breakfast of applesauce, yogurt, and definitely-not-maple (but passable) syrup and still keep things under 45g of carbs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s this all about?</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 06:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Who am I? My name is Chris Petersen.
I graduated from the stereotypical social awkwardness a long time ago and now focus my attention on things that a lot of us recovering nerds enjoy: family, food, friends, beer, and a little smattering of technology (I can’t stray too far from my roots). That said, I’m still a total geek, in both the old nerdy definition as well as the newer &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; meaning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>keeping your digital life secure</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/keeping-your-digital-life-secure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2012 07:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/keeping-your-digital-life-secure/</guid>
      <description>There have been a number of high-profile stories recently about hacking and digital identity theft, along with a rash of hacked yahoo.com email accounts that usually lead to scams/cons. When a number of my friends and family members fell victim to these hacks (thankfully not to the scams) and discovered that the collateral damage could be worse than the hack itself, I decided that I should put together some recommendations to help them avoid more trouble in the future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plus addressing for email</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/plus-addressing-for-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2010 08:01:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/plus-addressing-for-email/</guid>
      <description>Like most tech-savvy people, I have more than a handful of email addresses, and I like to guard them against being shared without my permission (and track back to the company that did the sharing). When you run your own mail server, this is quite easy &amp;ndash; just make up a custom email address for every company you do business with. Unfortunately, this gets somewhat cumbersome after awhile, and definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t a solution for the general public.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tor&#39;s Hard Cider Recipe</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2008 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough people ask about a simple cider recipe that I decided to post it here. This recipe originates from my friend Tor, and is definitely not the finest of brews, but it&amp;rsquo;s one heck of a strong cider. So-called &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; brewers may scoff at the idea of using bread yeast, but keep in mind that things (flavor in particular) work differently with cider than beer or wine, and don&amp;rsquo;t knock it until you taste it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Fashioned Root Beer, with a twist</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2007 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</guid>
      <description>Sassafras is the &amp;ldquo;root&amp;rdquo; in root beer. However, in the mid-60&amp;rsquo;s, the FDA discovered that a chemical in sassafras called safrole caused cancer in rats, and proceded to ban its sale for edible uses. This sent the root beer industry into a frenzy trying to find a replacement flavor (they eventually came up with something that&amp;rsquo;s a combination of licorice root &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s not anise, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste like it &amp;ndash; and wintergreen).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>