<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Petersen</title>
    <link>http://ex-nerd.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Petersen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://ex-nerd.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Spicy Ginger Beer</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/ginger-beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/ginger-beer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I like spicy ginger beer.  Here is the recipe I came up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cup ginger juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; cup galangal ginger juice (see instructions below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cup ground sugar (sugar + blender, for better dissolving in cold liquid)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cup lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cup honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6   cup water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Use &amp;ldquo;greater galangal&amp;rdquo; (aka thai ginger).  To prepare galangal ginger juice, mix root with water in at least a 2:1 weight ratio (meaning 2 lbs of root to 1 lb water), blend then strain well, squeezing out all of the liquid using a tea towel or other strong non-absorbent fabric.  I do the same with normal ginger but without the added water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mix, carbonate.  Makes approx 2 litres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(one of the little ice cubes == &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;24&lt;/sub&gt; cup)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for 5 gallons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12-15 oz ginger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 cup brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8-9 cups sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;thinly slice the ginger and put into a pot with sugar and 1-2 gallons of
water..  boil this gently for a LONG time (1+ hours), stirring
occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;right before you pour this into the keg to mix with more water, add:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 tbsp lemon juice (just shy of &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; cup)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and that&amp;rsquo;s it.  :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tsp ginger juice (or more?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; cup (2 tbsp) simple syrup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cup water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mix (triple recipe for a good glass), cool, carbonate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;for a little over a half gallon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cup ginger juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cups  simple syrup (maybe slightly less)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 cups  water&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is about 1.5x more ginger than in the smaller recipe, but I personally
think it will taste much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s this all about?</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2016 06:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-am-i:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Who am I?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my world.  It’s really not that bad of a place, actually.  My name is Chris Petersen and I’m proud to admit that I’m a bit of a nerd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated from the stereotypical social awkwardness a long time ago and now focus my attention on things that a lot of us 30-something recovering nerds enjoy:  family, food, friends, beer, and a little smattering of technology (I can’t stray too far from my roots).  That said, I’m still a total geek, in both the old nerdy definition as well as the newer &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the links in the sidebar aren&amp;rsquo;t enough for you to find a way to get in touch with me, you can send an email to &lt;code&gt;geek&lt;/code&gt; at this domain and it&amp;rsquo;ll find its way to my inbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you have something interesting to say (and to those recruiters out there, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t include &amp;ldquo;a job you might be interested in&amp;rdquo;), I might even reply.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resumé:  Chris Petersen</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 08:06:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/resume/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;!-- Updated: 2015-06-02 --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computer-skills:c59a67a3c7bc5faa453847420267045e&#34;&gt;COMPUTER SKILLS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Software Development:&lt;/h3&gt;
Advanced knowledge of Perl (20 years&lt;!-- 1995 --&gt;),Python (4 years&lt;!-- 2011 --&gt;), Java (2 years&lt;!-- 2012 --&gt;), Ruby/Rails (2 years&lt;!-- 2009 --&gt;), PHP (12 years&lt;!-- 2002 --&gt;), Javascript (11 years&lt;!-- 2002 --&gt;), UNIX shell scripting (14 years&lt;!-- 2000 --&gt;), and reading knowledge of Go, C, and C++.  Experience working with data exchange formats like XML, SOAP, and JSON via AJAX, XMLRPC, JSON-RPC, and REST.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Web Design:&lt;/h3&gt;  Expert level HTML, CSS, and Javascript (including
AJAX/JSON and libraries like jQuery), including semantic markup, as well as a great deal of experience with SEO (search engine optimization) and web-based user interface design.  Extremely comfortable working within MVC template frameworks like Rails, and administering Apache web servers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Database design:&lt;/h3&gt;
Considerable knowledge of design, administration, and performance tuning of MySQL.  Also experienced at designing databases and tuning queries for PostgreSQL and SQLite.  I also have experience with NoSQL and document-based systems like Memcached, Redis, CouchBase, Solr, and ElasticSearch (lucene).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Project Management:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scrumalliance.org/profiles/106925-chris-petersen&#34;&gt;Certified Scrum Master&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- #111943 --&gt;, and experience with Stanford design thinking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Linux system administration:&lt;/h3&gt;
I have administered Linux servers personally and professionally since 2000.  Aside from the software listed above, I also have experience managing Email, DNS, Samba, and many other Linux services and server applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Operating Systems:&lt;/h3&gt;
Linux (primarily Red Hat/Fedora/CentOS), Mac OS X, and Windows.
&lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Digital multimedia:&lt;/h3&gt;
Graphics (Gimp, Adobe Photoshop, and studio photography), audio/video codecs (see my open source contributions below), and web-based media delivery. --&gt;
&lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Networking hardware and software:&lt;/h3&gt;
Pulling and terminating category-5 and telephone wire, punch-down blocks, RJ-11 and RJ-45 jacks, signal tracing equipment, TCI/IP configuration on Linux, Macintosh, and Windows. --&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expert knowledge of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/STFW&#34;&gt;RTFM and STFW&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;relevant-experience-span-style-font-size-60-and-some-other-stuff-just-for-fun-span:c59a67a3c7bc5faa453847420267045e&#34;&gt;RELEVANT EXPERIENCE &lt;span style=&#34;font-size:60%&#34;&gt;(and some other stuff just for fun)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Sr. Applied Architect:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://nordstrom.com&#34;&gt;Nordstrom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;1/12/15 to present&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Helping design and build better mobile experiences for Nordstrom&amp;rsquo;s
                customers and salespeople alike, including the NEXT
                salesperson-to-customer texting app with TextStyle (text-to-buy),
                and other cool projects you could see soon online or in a store
                near you.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Executive Director / Lead Developer:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://schedulesdirect.org&#34;&gt;Schedules Direct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;07&lt;/sub&gt; to present (part time)&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Founding board member of nonprofit corporation that provides TV
                listings data to users of Open Source and free software, along
                with education about Free and Open Source software.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;!-- li&gt;Resigned from the board of directors in January of 2008 to take
                up the position of Chief Operations Officer.&lt;/li --&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Designed, implemented and maintain schedulesdirect.org website,
                using PHP, Perl, SOAP, CSS and Javascript technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;!-- li&gt;Currently designing a large-scale redundant content distribution
                system to distribute TV listings data to members&#39; approved
                software applications.&lt;/li --&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Coordinate and oversee work of other developers on the website and
                related services.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Oversee day to day business and financial operations.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Director / Owner:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://wingmanbrewers.com&#34;&gt;Wingman Brewers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Tacoma, WA, &lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; to present (weekends only)&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Board of Directors and part owner of this craft brewery.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Solutions Architect:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://realpage.com&#34;&gt;RealPage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;3/01/14 to 1/09/15&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Architect overseeing RealPage&amp;rsquo;s ActiveBuilding product as the team
                transitions from separate PHP and .NET applications to a modern
                Python 3 REST API and CoffeeScript-based single page web
                application.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Development Manager:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://realpage.com&#34;&gt;RealPage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;10/28/13 to 3/01/14&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Hire and lead the team of developers (and UI/UX designer) responsible for
                ActiveBuilding, a suite of web and mobile applications for multi-residence
                management and social networking.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Oversee and assist in development of traditional MVC PHP application while
                transitioning it to a more services oriented approach, including
                architecture of a new public REST API, and implementing a new Responsive
                CoffeeScript/JavaScript web application to eventually serve mobile and
                desktop browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Lead Software Development Engineer:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://activebuilding.com&#34;&gt;Active Building&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;12/3/12 to 10/28/13&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Hire and manage a team of developers to transition development of
                ActiveBuilding&amp;rsquo;s core PHP-based SaaS application away from 3rd party
                developers.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Guide future development of AB&amp;rsquo;s web application toward a more modern and
                robust service oriented architecture in support of internal and external
                REST API users, including responsive Angular.js web interface.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Implement agile SDLC, and increase fault tolerance by standardizing AWS
                provisioning and deployment via Chef.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Oversee agency and contractor development of mobile/responsive website and
                mobile apps.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Senior Software Engineer:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://realnetworks.com&#34;&gt;RealNetworks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;4/11/11 to &lt;!-- 2/3/12, 3/1/12 to --&gt; 11/15/12&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Senior engineer on a consumer media cloud service, including heavy
                integration with mobile/web clients and third party APIs (e.g. Facebook).
                Primarily responsible for Java/Jetty server and distributed asynchronous
                workers, along with designing a scalable JSON-RPC API.  Technologies used
                included PostgreSQL, Redis, RabbitMQ, Neo4j, noeqd, Heroku, Amazon S3, EC2.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Senior engineer and architect for Firefly, a social media-sharing
                application.  Responsible for all technical aspects of the project,
                from choice of primary language and frameworks to accompanying
                technologies like Elasticsearch, gearman, MySQL, and
                PostGIS. Project ended 2012-02.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Focused rough business requirements into a database schema and
                JSON-RPC API, then implemented these as scalable python web
                application and media processing framework.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Design and implement libraries for tight integration with
                third-party services like Facebook Graph API, Google Maps,
                OpenStreetMaps, and GeoNames.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Oversee development of mobile app, produced by third party contractor.
                &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Senior Software Engineer:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://marchex.com&#34;&gt;Marchex&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;9/01/08 to 4/08/11&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Senior engineer for Marchex Call Analytics team, responsible for
                maintaining a large Perl, Mason, and Javascript application and
                updating it to work with improvements to the supporting
                PostgreSQL, Asterisk, and Redis architecture.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;MCA team members are also responsible for upgrading the
                Ruby-based Call Mining platform from proof of concept to a
                product capable of real-world scale, processing and analyzing
                over 100k minutes of phone calls per month.
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Primary Engineer on Marchex&amp;rsquo;s Ruby-based Reputation Management
                product.  Duties included working closely with product managers
                and UI designers, as well as re-architecting the existing beta
                application to scale to an estimated 200,000 daily users after
                its public launch.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Technical Lead, overseeing development of PHP-, Perl-, and
                Java-based websites like Yellow.com and other directory sites
                operated by Marchex.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Technical Lead for the Marchex Business Profiles Pages team,
                which was a major contributor to Marchex&amp;rsquo;s winning of the 2009
                Search Engine Watch &amp;quot;Best SEM Technology Platform for SMBs&amp;quot;
                award.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Help design and implement web-based tools and sites for
                Marchex&amp;rsquo;s Publishing department.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Lead team of web developers to design and implement
                company-wide standards for HTML and CSS design, and SEO best
                practices.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Manage teams of 3-4 other developers.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Senior Software Developer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifloor.com/&#34;&gt;iFLOOR&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Tukwila, WA, &lt;i&gt;12/01/07 to 8/31/08&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Perl, HTML and PostgreSQL developer on iFLOOR.com&amp;rsquo;s custom ERP
                software and e-commerce website.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Upgrade legacy CVS revision control system to Subversion (SVN)
                and train others in its proper usage.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Development lead, &amp;ldquo;second chair&amp;rdquo; project manager, and SEO
                architect on redesigned iFLOOR.com website (June 2008).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Configure Bricolage content publishing system, and train users
                in some of its more advanced template features.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Replace antiquated True Spectra image manipulation/delivery
                system with tools based on ImageMagick and the Google Maps API.
                You can see a demo/tutorial about the zoom functionality
                &lt;a href=&#34;http://forevermore.net/articles/photo-zoom/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
                &lt;/li&gt;
             &lt;li&gt;Integrate Power Reviews product review system.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Lead Developer / Webmaster / Manager:
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.siliconmechanics.com/&#34;&gt;Silicon Mechanics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Bothell, WA, &lt;i&gt;11/01/02 through 11/30/07&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Design, implement, maintain and oversee development for a
                customized PHP- and MySQL-based solution for SiMech&amp;rsquo;s
                business/ERP/CRM process.  Aspects include pre-sale quotes,
                e-commerce and over-the-phone sales, support incident and
                RMA tracking, project and inventory management, customer
                management, and shipment invoicing and tracking.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Hire, train and manage a team developers and testers to assist
                with development and accommodate company growth from &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;02&lt;/sub&gt;
                employee count of 8 to 100+ employees by the time I left.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Set up and administer Apache and replicated MySQL servers.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Design the majority of graphics, HTML, CSS, Javascript, and
                other &amp;ldquo;look/feel&amp;rdquo; aspects of the siliconmechanics.com website
                as it looked from early 2004 until March of 2008 (though many of
                my user interface elements are still in place today).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Administer email, DNS and firewall servers (currently as
                backup administrator after passing duties off to full-time
                SysAdmin in &lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;06&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Photograph systems and other products, and perform any
                necessary digital post-processing (slowly transitioned these
                duties to product manager and graphic designer in 2006 and
                2007)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Help with system and rack integration when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li style=&#34;font-style: italic&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;05&lt;/sub&gt;, promoted from Developer/Webmaster
                to Sr. Developer upon hiring my first assistant developer.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Programmer: VersusLaw, Inc.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Redmond, WA, &lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;01&lt;/sub&gt; to &lt;sup&gt;11&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;02&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Designed and wrote Perl-based web robots designed for
                extracting legal information from various websites,
                including building a modular framework to facilitate
                creation of future robots.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Designed and implemented several modifications for the
                versuslaw.com search engine.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Chief Programmer:  Web Eye Technologies.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;96&lt;/sub&gt; to &lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;02&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Designed and developed an online shopping cart program
                using SQL and Perl DBI.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Expanded this program into a complete web-based website-design
                tool and content management system (CMS), designed to return the
                power of website creation to the hands of the small businesses
                and e-commerce users who own the sites, without requiring any
                special web-design knowledge on their part.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Technical Support:  Blue Mountain Internet.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Walla Walla, WA, &lt;i&gt;4/97 to 5/99&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Wrote custom programs in Perl, mostly for web use.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Answered questions about internet-related Macintosh and
                Windows problems.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Set up NAT-based internet access over existing networks at
                small businesses and a small school.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li --&gt;
    &lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Computer Lab Consultant:  Whitman College.&lt;/h3&gt;
         Walla Walla, WA, &lt;i&gt;9/95 to 9/98&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Installed, repaired and solved problems with Macintosh and
                  Windows-based computers and networks.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Answered questions and solved user problems with
                Macintosh, Microsoft and internet-based applications.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Technical Support:  Alternate Access.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;6/96 to 1/97&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Performed the same duties as at Blue Mountain Internet.
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Sales Associate:  Computer City.&lt;/h3&gt;
        Tacoma, WA, &lt;i&gt;6/95 to 8/95 and 12/95 to 1/96&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Diagnosed and repaired Macintosh systems and peripherals.
            &lt;li&gt;Sold and provided information about Macintosh and
                Windows-based computers, peripherals and software.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Computer/Network Technician:  University Place School
        District.&lt;/h3&gt;  Tacoma, WA, &lt;i&gt;1/94 to 6/95&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Installed several cat-5 ethernet networks from the ground
                up (pulling wire, installing RJ-45 jacks, hubs, ethernet
                cards, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Diagnosed and repaired Macintosh computers and
                peripherals.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Trained teachers and administrators in the use of
                Macintosh hardware, software and networks.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li --&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OPEN SOURCE DEVELOPMENT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Personal Projects on GitHub:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;I have a variety of open source projects
                &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ex-nerd/&#34;&gt;hosted at GitHub&lt;/a&gt;,
                designed for my own interests/needs as well as a few started
                on my own time to solve work-related needs.
                &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Steering Committee and Board Member:   &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythtv.org/&#34;&gt;MythTV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;8/10 to present&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Guide near- and long-term development efforts, including major architectural decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Coordinate projects and planning between developers located around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Project Maintainer:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythtv.org/wiki/Mythweb&#34;&gt;MythWeb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;6/03 to present&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Open Source (GPL) web interface to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythtv.org/&#34;&gt;MythTV&lt;/a&gt;,
                a popular DVR (Digital Video Recorder) application suite.  Written in a
                combination of PHP, Perl and Javascript.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;MythWeb has received rave reviews from LinuxJournal, LinuxTag
                and thousands of users around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Mentored a student to enhance MythWeb as part of Google&#39;s 2006
                Summer of Code.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Project Maintainer:  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythtv.org/wiki/Nuvexport&#34;&gt;nuvexport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
        Seattle, WA, &lt;i&gt;6/03 to present&lt;/i&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Open Source (GPL) program that interacts with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mythtv.org/&#34;&gt;MythTV&lt;/a&gt;,
                allowing its users to export recorded TV shows to a variety of more portable
                video formats.  Written in Perl.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Mentored a student as part of Google&#39;s 2006 Summer of Code to
                convert nuvexport into a C++ application natively integrated
                with the core video processing libraries used by MythTV.
                Unfortunately, this student dropped out before submitting any
                useful work.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;EDUCATION&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;The University of Chicago&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;, Chicago, IL&lt;br /&gt;
        Master of Arts in the Social Sciences&lt;br /&gt;
        Emphasis on South Asian Anthropology&lt;br /&gt;
        Graduated:  August, 2001&lt;!-- GPA: 3.40 --&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        &lt;h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;Whitman College&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;, Walla Walla, WA&lt;br /&gt;
        Bachelor of Arts in Philosophy&lt;br /&gt;
        Minors:  Psychology and Religion&lt;br /&gt;
        Graduated:  May, 1999&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OTHER SKILLS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Languages:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Near fluency in conversational Spanish.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Basic German.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Photography:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;General photographic skills, both technical and
                artistic&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Studio photography for inanimate objects (product shots,
                primarily of computer equipment).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Extensive experience in digital photography and digital
                photo reconstruction.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Archeological record keeping (pit and artifact
                documentation), and museum artifact photography.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Publication:  &lt;i&gt;Diario de Avisos:  Nov. 18, 1999&lt;/i&gt;,
                p. 29  (Newspaper:  Canary Islands, Spain).
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Leadership/Organizational:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Established and organized the Walla Walla, WA chapter of
                the Society for Creative Anachronism, with friends over a
                four-year period.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Served as Seneschal for three years during my time at
                Whitman College, which consisted of maintaining group
                organization, managing paperwork, meetings, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li --&gt;
    &lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Basic surveying:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Surveyed pyramids with a professional cartographer, for
                mapping and possible digital reconstruction.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Archeological skills:&lt;/h3&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Basic skills, including laying baulk string, drawing
                square diagrams, digging, filling out artifact tags, and
                cleaning pottery.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li --&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;INTERESTS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Linux&lt;/h3&gt;:  I have used Linux for a long time.  I am also a
        contributor to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://fedoraproject.org/&#34;&gt;Fedora Project&lt;/a&gt;
        and serve on the board of the
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.seagl.org/&#34;&gt;Seattle GNU Linux Conference&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Open Source Software&lt;/h3&gt;:  I am a firm believer in the value of
        Free Software, and am actively involved in several open source projects.
        You can see my major contributions listed above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Akili Dada&lt;/h3&gt;:  I served on the advisory council and still act as
        a technology advisor for this
        &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.akilidada.org/&#34; title=&#34;Akili Dada scholarships&#34;&gt;nonprofit organization&lt;/a&gt;
        dedicated to providing high-school scholarships to young women in
        Kenya.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Brewing&lt;/h3&gt;:  I&#39;m fascinated by all things fermented, and dabble
        with cider, mead, Belgian style beers, and the occasional homemade
        cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Medieval Reenactment&lt;/h3&gt;: I have participated with the Society for
        Creative Anachronism (an international not-for-profit organization
        dedicated to the study and reenactment of the middle ages) and other
        experimental archeology groups on and off since 1995, mostly as an
        excuse to go camping with good friends.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;!-- li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Outdoors&lt;/h3&gt;:  biking, backpacking, camping.&lt;/li --&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ARCHEOLOGICAL EXPERIENCE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Piramides de G&amp;uuml;&amp;iacute;mar&lt;/h3&gt;:  &lt;i&gt;November, 1999&lt;/i&gt;.
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;3 weeks of digging on the island of Tenerife (Canary
                Islands, Spain).&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Directed by Dr. Thor Heyerdahl.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Surveyed pyramids for map-making, worked as dig
                photographer, and spent some time digging and
                sifting.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Khirbet Cana&lt;/h3&gt;:  &lt;i&gt;July and August, 1998&lt;/i&gt;.
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;5 weeks of digging in Israel with the University of Puget
                Sound.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Detailed daily lectures on archeology, early Galilean
                culture and Biblical scholarship.&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Archeological tours led by local experts to many of the
                ruins in and around the Galilee.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>keeping your digital life secure</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/keeping-your-digital-life-secure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2012 07:33:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/keeping-your-digital-life-secure/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There have been a number of high-profile stories recently about hacking and digital identity theft, along with a rash of hacked yahoo.com email accounts that usually lead to scams/cons. When a number of my friends and family members fell victim to these hacks (thankfully not to the scams) and discovered that the collateral damage could be worse than the hack itself, I decided that I should put together some recommendations to help them avoid more trouble in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep reading for a thorough explanation of how to recover from these email hacks, along with a bunch of recommendations for how to limit the chance of them happening, or the damage done if they do occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-scam:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;The scam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the scams I&amp;rsquo;ve seen from these hacked accounts are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/#q=stranded+traveler+scam&#34;&gt;stranded traveler scams&lt;/a&gt;. The scammer sends an email purporting to be your friend, mugged and stranded in some foreign country with no cash to pay for a hotel or buy tickets home (yet somehow they still have their computer to send email!).  When you reply to ask your friend for more information, your reply is actually redirected to the scammer, who set up a sneaky Reply-To address on the original email that looks almost identical to the correct one.  For example, if your friend&amp;rsquo;s email address is &lt;code&gt;user@example.com&lt;/code&gt;, the reply-to address might be &lt;code&gt;userr@example.com&lt;/code&gt; (notice the second r?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when you reply to your friend, either to ask how they&amp;rsquo;re doing, or even just to tell them that their account has been hacked, they never even get the message.  When you reply to one of these kinds of messages, it&amp;rsquo;s safest to address a new email to your friend, so that you can be sure that you are sending the message to the correct person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are the one who got hacked, your priorities should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change your password and clear out that bogus reply-to address (here&amp;rsquo;s how to do it for &lt;a href=&#34;http://email.about.com/od/yahoomailtips/qt/et_reply_to.htm&#34;&gt;yahoo&lt;/a&gt; and [gmail]&lt;a href=&#34;http://support.google.com/mail/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;amp;answer=7991))&#34;&gt;http://support.google.com/mail/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;amp;answer=7991))&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact as many friends as you can to let them know &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; to reply to the bogus/scam email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact your email provider to let them know about the hack, and about the bogus email address that has likely been set up to collect all of your friends&amp;rsquo; replies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change your password anywhere else that you use your email address to log in (e.g. facebook, twitter, amazon.com).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figure out what (if anything) the hacker deleted from your email account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;passwords:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;Passwords&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you choose a new password, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that most of the passwords we use are &lt;a title=&#34;A great XKCD comic about password strength.&#34; href=&#34;http://xkcd.com/936/&#34;&gt;hard for humans to remember and fairly easy for a computer to guess&lt;/a&gt;.  Take a look at the comic linked to from the previous sentence before you choose a new password.  It&amp;rsquo;s a lot easier for you to remember four words (e.g. &amp;ldquo;correct horse battery staple&amp;rdquo;) than a bunch of semi-random characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to take things a step further, check out a password vault like &lt;a href=&#34;https://agilebits.com/onepassword&#34;&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt;.  At $50, it&amp;rsquo;s fairly expensive, but it&amp;rsquo;s also very easy to use, and has tools to help create and organize those large random-character passwords that you still need to occasionally use because a lot of websites don&amp;rsquo;t actually let you use long passwords.  I was finally convinced of its worth when I realized that my wife had no way to access any of our financial information if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t around to help (yes, I&amp;rsquo;ve reached that point in life where I feel the need to take precautions against things like getting run over by high speed vehicles).  It only took a few minutes to show her how to use 1Password, and now her computer and phone have access to all of the same passwords that mine do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use GMail and want to be extra-secure, look into turning on &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.google.com/accounts/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;amp;amp;answer=180744&#34;&gt;2-Step Verification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;backups:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;Backups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major email providers like Yahoo, Google, or Microsoft make &lt;strong&gt;no assurances&lt;/strong&gt; that the data stored on their servers is safe from accidental deletion.  It&amp;rsquo;s unlikely, but not unheard of, for accounts to randomly disappear or users to find their inboxes suddenly empty.  Even if you have no fear of your email account getting hacked, you should at least trust in the small chance that your email may someday vanish or be locked away where you can&amp;rsquo;t get at it.  Feel free to keep your email around as an archive, but if you have important documents that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to lose, make sure you download them to your own computer where you can be sure they will be backed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say &amp;ldquo;backup&amp;rdquo;, I usually refer to &amp;ldquo;remote backups&amp;rdquo;, meaning storing your backup files somewhere far away.  Local backups like Apple&amp;rsquo;s Time Machine are great (you can never have too many backups, and local backups make for much faster recovery), but they won&amp;rsquo;t get you your files back if your computer is stolen or if your house burns down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, there are two kinds of remote backups, too.  Easy-access services like Dropbox or Google Drive can provide free storage for your files, and allow easy access from multiple locations, but they usually have the same disclaimers as email providers, releasing them of responsibility if your files ever fail to appear.  However, I still encourage you to look into one or more of these services (there are others, but these are the top three):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://db.tt/zxULLdP&#34;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;: At 2GB free, Dropbox gives you the least amount of free storage (though you can add some additional space for free by doing things like completing their online tutorial), but their user experience is by far the best, and by referrals and other gimmicks, you can get considerably more free storage.  This is probably the most popular provider (it&amp;rsquo;s certainly my favorite), especially because of how easy they make it to share files (it took me under a minute to set up a folder for my whole family to share photos, including showing my parents how it worked).  &lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: the link provided is a referral link.  If you sign up via my link, each of us will receive an additional 500M of free storage space once you install the app.  I&amp;rsquo;m more than happy to admit my bias toward you choosing Dropbox first.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/intl/en_US/drive/start/index.html&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;: Google Drive is a new addition to Google Docs, their web-based word processor, spreadsheet, and other office tools.  If you have a Google account, you already have a Google Drive with at least 15GB of storage and just need to download and run the application on your computer.  Choose this one if you use Google Docs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/skydrive/home&#34;&gt;Microsoft SkyDrive&lt;/a&gt;: Like Google, Microsoft uses SkyDrive to integrate with their web-based office tools.  They also give you a total 7GB of space to store your files.  If you use a lot of Microsoft products, this is probably your best bet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these services include applications that you can install on your computer and smartphone.  They work by creating a folder on your computer to synchronize, and any file you put there will find its way to their servers.  Even better, these services will keep your files in sync between all of your computers, if you happen to have more than one.  If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to decide right away which one to use, there&amp;rsquo;s no reason that you can&amp;rsquo;t run more than one at the same time (I have accounts with all of them, though I only run Dropbox on my computer/phone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For true backups, I recommend &lt;a href=&#34;http://crashplan.com/&#34;&gt;CrashPlan&lt;/a&gt;.  There are other services out there, but I won&amp;rsquo;t even bother providing comparisons (there are plenty of other sites out there to do that).  If you keep around an external hard drive, their free software will handle your local backups, and will even let you share your hard drive out to friends and family to trade backup space (e.g. offer to back up each other&amp;rsquo;s most important files), keeping your things encrypted so that your friends will only host the files but never be able to see their contents.  Most importantly, their monthly rates are more than reasonable if you would like to back your files up to their own servers (at most $5/month for unlimited storage for one computer, and as low as $1.50/month if you have under 10GB of files to back up).  They even have a reasonably-priced &amp;ldquo;Family Plan&amp;rdquo; that allows you to protect up to 10 computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a true backup service, CrashPlan makes assurances that your files will be there when you need them, keeps them encrypted so no one but you will ever see the contents, allows you to use extremely secure passwords, and offers a number of concierge style services (e.g. for a reasonable fee, they will mail you a hard drive containing your requested backup restore files).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least, go out and buy yourself some USB thumb drives and/or an external hard drive, and use the free version of CrashPlan to copy files over every few weeks.  If you go with a thumb drive or two, make sure to keep at least one of them somewhere other than your computer (e.g. at work or in your car&amp;rsquo;s glove box).  CrashPlan&amp;rsquo;s encryption will keep your personal information safe even if someone else happens to run across the disk and tries to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;email:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;Email&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the big free email hosts these days seem to provide a way to connect up a standalone email program via &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imap&#34;&gt;IMAP&lt;/a&gt;.  If you run Windows, then Outlook Express is already installed.  On MacOS, Apple&amp;rsquo;s included Mail.app program will do the job nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to know about IMAP is that it only mirrors the email that&amp;rsquo;s on the server.  This means that if something or someone deletes the files on the server, your local mail program will happily synchronize up that empty mail box.  What you &lt;strong&gt;do&lt;/strong&gt; get with these programs is an easy way to back up (and to some extent, restore) your mail data, as long as you remember to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are instructions for &lt;a href=&#34;http://support.microsoft.com/kb/270670&#34;&gt;Outlook Express&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maclife.com/article/howtos/how_back_and_restore_mail_lion&#34;&gt;Mail.app&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://kb.mozillazine.org/Importing_and_exporting_your_mail&#34;&gt;Thunderbird&lt;/a&gt; (which is a great free email client for Mac, Windows, and Linux).  Remember that if you subscribe to a backup service like CrashPlan, exporting to a folder on your hard drive means your mail archives will get backed up along with everything else, and a good provider like CrashPlan will even let you restore them from specific points in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m personally a big fan of &lt;a href=&#34;http://mail.google.com/mail/signup&#34;&gt;GMail&lt;/a&gt; (not to mention all of Google&amp;rsquo;s other great free services), so don&amp;rsquo;t feel too bad ditching Yahoo or that @comcast.net email address that came with your internet connection if you want something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;browsers:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;Browsers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be a big deal for techie folks to try to push their friends/relatives to use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mozilla.org/firefox/&#34;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/chrome/&#34;&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, but in all honesty the latest versions of Internet Explorer (Windows) and Safari (Mac) are actually pretty secure.  The most important thing to remember is to &lt;strong&gt;keep your browser up to date&lt;/strong&gt;.  If you run an older version of Windows or MacOS, then I would highly recommend taking a look at Firefox or Chrome, since their engineers keep them up to date with the latest security patches a lot faster than Microsoft and Apple supply new versions of browsers to old computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-s-it:2a8e6e3e21ba6986b35f2fe5d0e95ba5&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this was a bit long, but I&amp;rsquo;ve actually tried to keep it as lightweight as possible (it&amp;rsquo;s far from a comprehensive overview of every option out there) while still providing good information that covers more than just my personal favorites.  If you take anything away from this, please let it be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use strong passwords.&lt;/strong&gt;  Numbers and symbols are great, but longer passwords are better than short ones full of random characters you can&#39;t easily remember.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep your software up to date.&lt;/strong&gt;  Software engineers work hard to keep their software free of security holes, but it won&#39;t help you unless you actually get the latest versions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back up your files.&lt;/strong&gt;  Pay for a service and/or buy yourself a handful of USB thumb drives to store your most important files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the links for this page were found with a quick web search, so please let me know in the comments if they ever stop working and I will find new/better ones.  Only the &lt;a href=&#34;http://db.tt/zxULLdP&#34;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; link contains any sort of referral that might be perceived to benefit me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>plus addressing for email</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/plus-addressing-for-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2010 08:01:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/tech/plus-addressing-for-email/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Like most tech-savvy people, I have more than a handful of email addresses, and I like to guard them against being shared without my permission (and track back to the company that did the sharing).  When you run your own mail server, this is quite easy &amp;ndash; just make up a custom email address for every company you do business with.  Unfortunately, this gets somewhat cumbersome after awhile, and definitely isn&amp;rsquo;t a solution for the general public.  Enter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plus_addressing#Sub-addressing&#34;&gt;plus addressing&lt;/a&gt;, a method built into most mail servers that allows users to modify their own email addresses with additional data that can be tracked but does not interfere with mail delivery.  This would be the perfect solution if it was actually supported by the majority of online account providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The technique for plus addressing is simple:  add a plus and a word after the username portion of your email address.  For example, &lt;code&gt;exnerd@example.com&lt;/code&gt; would become &lt;code&gt;exnerd+shopping@example.com&lt;/code&gt;.  This way, you can create a custom email address for certain types of transactions, or even for every company you do business with online.  The format is well-documented and supported by my favorite &lt;a href=&#34;http://gmailblog.blogspot.com/2008/03/2-hidden-ways-to-get-more-from-your.html&#34;&gt;free email provider&lt;/a&gt;.  It works great, too, until you run into a company that knows very little about technology.  Like all of my credit card companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even without the feature of using the plus to create an ignored portion of the email address, the plus character has been valid for use in email addresses since &lt;a href=&#34;http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc822&#34;&gt;RFC 822&lt;/a&gt;, which was written in 1982!  That RFC has been replaced a few times (the current is &lt;a href=&#34;http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6854&#34;&gt;RFC 6854&lt;/a&gt;), but support for the plus character hasn&amp;rsquo;t changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I would highly recommend using plus addressing to sort and track your incoming mail.  I would also recommend that whenever you run into a so-called technologically-adept company like one of my credit card providers to ask them why they are violating an email standard that is almost 30 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tor&#39;s Hard Cider Recipe</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2008 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough people ask about a simple cider recipe that I&amp;rsquo;m just going
to post it here.  This recipe originates from my friend
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.welandsmithy.com/&#34;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;, and is definitely not the finest
of brews, but it&amp;rsquo;s one &lt;b&gt;heck&lt;/b&gt; of a strong cider.  So-called &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; brewers
may scoff at the idea of using bread yeast, but keep in mind that things (most
importantly flavor)  work differently with cider than beer or wine, and don&amp;rsquo;t
knock it until you taste it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you will need the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 gallon 100% apple juice (in a &lt;strong&gt;glass&lt;/strong&gt; bottle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 packet bread yeast (eg. Fleishman&amp;rsquo;s or Red Star) &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#note1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4-6 cups brown and/or white sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 party balloon (buy a pack &amp;ndash; sometimes they break) &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#note2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;font-size: 80%&#34;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;note1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Hard-core brewers may scoff at the use of bread yeast here but it works well enough.  Of course, you&#39;re more than welcome to substitute a beer, cider, or ale yeast.  It will change the flavor of the end result, so you might want to try several different yeasts to see which you prefer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;font-size: 80%&#34;&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;note2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Of course, you can also use a standard brewing airlock.  They only cost about $2 and can be picked up at any brew store.  Just make sure that you get a rubber stopper big enough not to fall through the opening on the juice bottle
(7&amp;frac12; or 8 will probably do the trick, but I recommend that you measure to be sure).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, follow these relatively simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pour off a glass or so worth of apple juice and set it aside (you&amp;rsquo;ll need some of it in a bit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put the sugar into a saucepan.  More sugar means a sweeter cider and more alcohol, darker sugar means a darker cider with a stronger flavor. I like about 4.5 cups, half dark-brown and half white sugar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add enough apple juice to the saucepan to dissolve the sugar over low heat.  You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t need more than half of the remaining cider.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the sugar is dissolved, let the mixture cool until until it&amp;rsquo;s not hot enough to burn you (or the yeast), and pour it back into the bottle (use a funnel if you need to).  The bottle should now be full of warm extra-sweet juice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Toss in about &amp;frac12; tsp of yeast (a yeast packet usually holds a little over 2 tsp, so don&amp;rsquo;t throw the whole thing in), and top off the bottle with the juice you set aside in step 1.  Leave a few inches at the top of the bottle &amp;ndash; don&amp;rsquo;t let it get too full.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wash the powdered anti-stick stuff out of the balloon, and prick it with a pin.  Then place the balloon on top of the bottle.  The pin-prick will be enough to let air escape from the bottle, but not big enough to let any nasty bacteria back in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it!  Let this sit for 2-3 weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2-3 weeks, you will need to &amp;ldquo;rack&amp;rdquo; the cider.  Racking is the process of
siphoning the cider off the top of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lees&#34;&gt;lees&lt;/a&gt; (dead yeast).  You can use a siphon if you want, but if you&amp;rsquo;re careful the 1-gallon bottle is small enough that you can usually just pour the good stuff off the top.  Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if you get a little lees along with the cider, since you have to rack it again, anyway. Replace the balloon (using a new one if necessary) and let the cider continue to ferment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rack the cider again every 2-3 weeks until there is no more lees at the bottom
of the bottle.  The cider is drinkable at any stage, but it starts to get good
at about 2-3 months, and excellent around 9 months (and so far, I&amp;rsquo;ve only seen
it get better with age).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Important: Please make sure that you do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; reseal the juice bottle with
its original lid until you are &lt;strong&gt;completely sure&lt;/strong&gt; that there is no live
yeast left. This kind of bottle was not made to handle pressure, and if you have &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; live yeast left over, you risk building up more pressure than the
bottle can handle. Since the cap screws on stronger than the glass can hold, if
it blows, you&amp;rsquo;ll end up with sticky broken glass all over your kitchen (or
wherever you chose to set your brew). Trust me, you don&amp;rsquo;t want that.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. If you would like to read a more detailed story and recipe about apples and cider, check out this blog post about my first
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pieofthetiger.com/2009/11/apple-pressing-party/&#34;&gt;apple pressing party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Fashioned Root Beer, with a twist</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2007 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sassafras is the &amp;ldquo;root&amp;rdquo; in root beer. However, in the mid-60&amp;rsquo;s, the FDA
discovered that a chemical in sassafras called
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safrole&#34;&gt;safrole&lt;/a&gt; caused cancer in rats, and
proceded to ban its sale for edible uses. This sent the root beer industry into
a frenzy trying to find a replacement flavor (they eventually came up with
something that&amp;rsquo;s a combination of licorice root &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; anise, and
doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste like it &amp;ndash; and wintergreen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people (myself included) believe that safrole is only dangerous when
extracted from the sassafras root itself (there is a common theory is in herbal
medicine that there are other chemicals present in the plant that cancel out the
harmful effects of things like safrole).  Thus, I don&amp;rsquo;t mind drinking a little
&amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; root beer &amp;ndash; if it does happen to be harmful, the small amounts that I
drink won&amp;rsquo;t be that bad for me (couldn&amp;rsquo;t be worse than something like alcohol).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scouring books and the web for a good traditional root beer recipe, and
failing to come up with something really good, I eventually merged several
recipes together to come up with the following, which has a lot of the taste of
a traditional root beer, but also includes some wintergreen to make it more
compatible with the modern palate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, put about 5 quarts of water into your favorite brew pot, and then add:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 oz sarsparilla root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 oz sassafras root bark&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#sassafras&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 oz cherry bark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; oz licorice root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp freshly ground nutmeg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt; oz cinnamon (about half a stick)&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#cinnamon&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 to 4 oz raisins (you can add more if you like their flavor)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 cups honey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; cup molasses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 lb sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simmer this mixture for an hour or so, until you have a 5 quarts or so of syrup
left in your pot (remember, adding all that stuff increased your volume by a
couple of quarts).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this is boiled down, strain your mixture into another pot and add:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tbsp vanilla extract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp wintergreen or birch extract, or &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp pure essential oil
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#wintergreen&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stir a bit, and then bottle in 1-quart jars.  Due to the high sugar content,
this should keep fairly well, but you could always use a plastic jar or bottle
and store it in the freezer (do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; put glass into the freezer).  To make
the root beer, just mix 1:4 with water (one part syrup + 4 parts water) and
carbonate&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#carbonate&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Depending on your taste preference,
variations in cooking times, and/or the spices you used, you may find that the
ratio needs to be adjusted for your batch, so don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to use more or less
syrup to get the flavor just right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;font-size: 80%&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;sassafras&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Sassafras root bark (not plain old bark) is illegal for sale as a food product
in the US because it&amp;rsquo;s been shown, like many things, to cause cancer in lab
rats. However, many brew stores carry the Brewer&amp;rsquo;s Garden brand of sassafras
&amp;ldquo;potpouri&amp;rdquo;, or you can get it directly from one of several bulk herb suppliers
online.  Please see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chow.com/stories/10129&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; for a more
in depth explanation about the ban.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;cinnamon&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
What you buy in stores is actually cassia, not cinnamon.  If you can&amp;rsquo;t get ahold
of &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; cinnamon, you might want to use a smaller amount than the one listed
in the recipe.  However, &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; cinnamon can usually be found in the Mexican
section of the grocery store as &amp;ldquo;canela&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;wintergreen&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
I initially tried wintergreen oil, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t dissolve well. I did
eventually find a good all-natural wintergreen extract (made by Boyajian) at a
local fruit market, though you&amp;rsquo;ll also have luck buying it from cake-decorating
supply places (as it was a frosting-flavor additive).  Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned
that you can use gum arabic as an emulsifier to allow the oil and sugar solution
to stay mixed.  Just mix the oil with a tsp or so of gum arabic, and then add a
tbsp or two of water as you quickly stir.  Once this is mixed, you can just add
it to the recipe like you would an extract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VERY Important&lt;/strong&gt;:  If you use essential oil, make sure that you are using
&lt;strong&gt;food grade&lt;/strong&gt; ingredients.  This means that you want 100% pure essential oil
and food grade gum arabic (do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; get it from an art supply store). There
are many herb and health food shops online that sell both ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;carbonate&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend the money on a carbon dioxide tank and injection
system, you can &amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rdquo; and just mix the syrup straight into carbonated water
from a can or bottle.  If you do this, compare the different flavors of plain
carbonated versus &amp;ldquo;soda water&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;club soda&amp;rdquo;.  The latter two usually have
baking soda added to counteract the mild acid generated during the carbonation
process, which some people think gives carbonated water an unpleasant tart
flavor (but which contributes to the flavor of many carbonated beverages).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;license&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a rel=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Creative Commons License&#34; style=&#34;border-width:0; float:left; margin: .75em 1em 0 0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-sa/4.0/88x31.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    This &lt;span xmlns:dc=&#34;http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/&#34; property=&#34;dc:title&#34;&gt;recipe&lt;/span&gt; by
    &lt;a xmlns:cc=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/ns#&#34; href=&#34;http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/&#34; property=&#34;cc:attributionName&#34; rel=&#34;cc:attributionURL&#34;&gt;Chris Petersen&lt;/a&gt;
    is licensed under a&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;a rel=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>