<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food on Chris Petersen</title>
    <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Food on Chris Petersen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 20:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://ex-nerd.com/food/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Low Carb Waffles</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/low-carb-waffles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/low-carb-waffles/</guid>
      <description>Living with Type 1 Diabetes means that I have to closely watch my carbohydrate intake, and it&amp;rsquo;s easier to do this by eating low-carb foods that make the math easier. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up on some of the finer things in life &amp;ndash; like waffles &amp;ndash; I spent some time formulating a decent substitute for carb-heavy grain-based waffles. This lets me have a fairly large breakfast of applesauce, yogurt, and definitely-not-maple (but passable) syrup and still keep things under 45g of carbs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tor&#39;s Hard Cider Recipe</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2008 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/hard-cider-recipe/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough people ask about a simple cider recipe that I decided to post it here. This recipe originates from my friend Tor, and is definitely not the finest of brews, but it&amp;rsquo;s one heck of a strong cider. So-called &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; brewers may scoff at the idea of using bread yeast, but keep in mind that things (flavor in particular) work differently with cider than beer or wine, and don&amp;rsquo;t knock it until you taste it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Fashioned Root Beer, with a twist</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jul 2007 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/food/root-beer/</guid>
      <description>Sassafras is the &amp;ldquo;root&amp;rdquo; in root beer. However, in the mid-60&amp;rsquo;s, the FDA discovered that a chemical in sassafras called safrole caused cancer in rats, and proceded to ban its sale for edible uses. This sent the root beer industry into a frenzy trying to find a replacement flavor (they eventually came up with something that&amp;rsquo;s a combination of licorice root &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s not anise, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t taste like it &amp;ndash; and wintergreen).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
