<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>diabetes on Chris Petersen</title>
    <link>http://ex-nerd.com/tags/diabetes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in diabetes on Chris Petersen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 20:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ex-nerd.com/tags/diabetes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Kinds of Diabetes: Car Analogy</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/kinds_of_diabetes_car_analogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/kinds_of_diabetes_car_analogy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Diabetes Mellitus is a 500 year old term that describes the sweet-smelling urine
of people whose bodies have stopped being able to regulate blood sugar properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now know that it refers to a family of different (and largely unrelated)
diseases that all have the same symptoms before doctors can determine what has
caused them. People &amp;ndash; even doctors &amp;ndash; still have trouble understanding the
differences between these diseases, so I tried to come up with a simple and
(hopefully) humerous analogy by thinking of each disease as a problem with your
car.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type 1 Diabetes Name History</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/t1_name_history/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/t1_name_history/</guid>
      <description>This page is sort of a living document about my research into the naming history of autoimmune diabetes mellitus, more commonly known as Type 1 Diabetes.
There are obviously a lot of missing sections but I&amp;rsquo;ve been promising to get this posted for several years and I figure this is the best way to encourage myself to finish.
Diabetes Mellitus The name &amp;ldquo;Diabetes Mellitus&amp;rdquo; dates back roughly 500 years, and awarness of the disease by other names (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Participate in Clinical Research!</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/clinical_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 20:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/clinical_research/</guid>
      <description>Photos like this one are fairly common in Type 1 Diabetes forums, usually accompanied by a comment like &amp;ldquo;DKA sucks!&amp;quot;, making light of the extremely unpleasant and occasionally deadly Diabetic Ketoacidosis. I decided to post a similar photo but with a positive story behind it. So this is me, sitting in a hospital bed in the research wing of a local hospital while they spent several hours measuring how my body reacts when I drink a high carb/protein shake and don&amp;rsquo;t take insulin for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Type 1 Diabetes Resources</title>
      <link>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 08:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ex-nerd.com/diabetes/resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I plan to eventually write about a bunch of these topics individually.  Until then,
here is my collection of links to a number of diabetes-releated topics that I have found
especially helpful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>